Something incredible is happening right
now during the war in Ukraine. More than
12 years after Russia first invaded and
seized control over the Crimean
Peninsula, Moscow's grip over the
territory is finally beginning to slip.
Near the end of May, the Ukrainian armed
forces announced that they were adopting
a new strategy towards the Russian
occupation in Crimea that they called a
logistics lockdown. Unable to take
Crimea back with troops on the ground,
they were going to use their new
mid-range explosive drones to
systematically target Russia's
logistics, warehouses, equipment,
infrastructure, and supply routes going
in and out of Crimea at operational
depth instead. In effect, this new
Ukrainian strategy aimed to transform
Crimea's geography from a Russian
strength into a Russian weakness by
isolating it as much as possible from
the rest of Russia and Russian occupied
territory. In June, Ukraine's defense
minister, Mkhyo Fenerov, claimed during
an interview on YouTube that this new
strategy aimed to effectively transform
Crimea into an island, which if
successful, would have devastating
consequences for both the Russian
military operating on the front lines
and for Russian society at large. And so
far, this new Ukrainian strategy has
proven to be extremely successful.
You see, the Crimean Peninsula is
geographically speaking already almost
an island naturally. It is only
tenuously connected to the rest of the
European continent in the north through
land by the extremely narrow ismas of
Paraccom, which only ranges between 5
and 7 km wide. Other than this one
natural connection, the rest of Crimea
separated from southern Ukraine by the
seivage or the rotten sea, a complex
labyrinth of shallow lagoons, salt
marshes, and wetlands that are
incredibly difficult to traverse over.
Other than the ismas of Paracop, there
are basically only two other places
across the seash that are both wide and
firm enough to actually handle roads and
railways. Meaning that there are really
only three narrow logistical corridors
between southern Ukraine and Crimea that
land-based logistics can travel across
its scale through the ismiss of Paracop
in the west, through Chongar in the
center, and across the Arab spit in the
east. After Russia seized control over
Crimea in early 2014, this geography
posed a serious challenge for the
Kremlin to deal with since there was no
connection to it by land to the rest of
Russia. Russia sort of solved this
problem by building a $4 billion bridge
to Crimea from Cranadar Cry across the
Kurd straight, which features a highway
that was finished in 2018 and a railway
that was finished near the end of 2019.
But it still wasn't enough to fully
logistically support Crimea's population
of more than two and a half million
people. And Russia's expanding military
presence on the peninsula. Russia spent
billions of more dollars heavily
militarizing Crimea after the 2014
conquest with new military bases, radar
stations, airfields, naval
infrastructure, and garrisons that all
enabled the Russian military to have a
large base of operations to invade and
attack southern Ukraine from during the
2022 invasion. While since then, Crimea
has also given the Russians a rear base
to support their military operations all
along the southern frontfront. One of
Russia's principal objectives for having
invaded Ukraine again in 2022 was
establishing a direct land corridor to
Crimea across southern Ukraine through
the Donets, Zaparisia, and Hanolasts in
order to make Crimea less of a
logistical island for them and to
solidify their control over it. Now,
since the invasion, the principal
methods that the Russians have used to
reinforce Crimea with supplies and
troops have been through this web of
roads and rail lines through the
occupied land bridge in southern
Ukraine, through the $4 billion Crimean
bridge that they built across the Kirch
Strait, and through fairies and maritime
base logistics. And all of these
connections have beun being relentlessly
and routinely attacked by the Ukrainians
recently. Before the start of the
current strategy to cut Crimea off from
the rest of Russia, the Ukrainians
repeatedly attacked the bridge across
the Kurd straight first, but with only
limited successes. A truck bomb the
Ukrainians blew up on the highway part
of the bridge in October of 2022 knocked
out two sections of it and resulted in
months worth of repairs. Road traffic
across the bridge was severely disrupted
by the attack for months, but rail
traffic continued relatively quickly
afterward. In July of 2023, Ukrainian
naval drones attacked the bridge again
overnight, collapsing one of its
sections in the process. But like the
first attack, while it managed to
disrupt road traffic across the bridge
for months, rail traffic was minimally
affected and was restored again within
hours. Then in June of 2025, the
Ukrainians reported that they had
secretly planted and detonated
explosives beneath the bridge along
several of its underwater support
structures, but the damage inflicted was
minimal and only resulted in the halt of
traffic on the bridge for a few hours.
The bridge has more or less remained
open to both vehicle and rail traffic
ever since then, but the repeated
Ukrainian attacks on it did force the
Russians into restricting the bridgeg's
use. After the 2022 truck bomb attack,
the Russian authorities introduced a ban
on any trucks carrying a payload of more
than one and a half tons in most
commercial vans from utilizing it in
order to prevent another similar attack
and also reduce the reliance on large
fuel shipments by rail across the bridge
to eliminate the presence of potentially
flammable materials on it. It's still
being used as a logistics corridor by
the Russians in a Crimea, but the bulk
of Russia's heavy freight routes were
transferred towards the web of roads and
railways across the land bridge through
occupied southern Ukraine and on board
fairies instead with airbased logistics
effectively having been shut down since
the start of the war due to both sides's
advanced anti-air systems. And as
Ukraine's drone technology and
innovation continued advancing with the
help of Starlink and US-made AI powered
Hornet drones, their increasingly
capable fleet of mid and longrange
drones eventually enabled them to begin
reliably and consistently attacking all
of these alternative supply routes into
Crimea as well. Since April of this
year, the Ukrainians have launched
hundreds of mid-range drone attacks
against Russian trucks carrying fuel,
ammunition, and supplies all along the
strategically critical R280 highway that
connects the Russian mainland to Crimea
through the occupied cities of Marupole,
Malipole, and Chongar onwards towards
the major Crimean cities of Symphopole
and Sevastapole. And besides for
targeting Russian trucks and railways
themselves, the drones have been
dropping numerous small landmines all
along the highway that weigh only 500 g
that have magnetic or motion sensors
that are blowing up additional trucks
later. The Russian occupation
authorities like to call this highway
the Novaria highway, but lately the
Ukrainians have increasingly begun
referring to it as the highway of death
instead.
By June, Ukraine's third special
battalion claimed to have taken full
aerial control over the stretch of the
highway between Molapool and Chongar
accompanied by videos of dozens of
exploding and burning Russian trucks
that they had taken out with their
drones. The bridge itself from Chongar
leading into Crimea was struck by
Ukrainian drones at least three separate
times in June alone, critically damaging
it and forcing the Russians to switch
traffic across a pontoon bridge nearby
instead. Then around 50 of Russia's
trucks carrying fuel and ammunition that
were diverted away from Chongar through
the Paricopismas were then further
struck by Ukrainian drones on the 11th
of June as they were attempting to cross
through Ardian. All in all, since this
new Ukrainian mid-range drone campaign
began ramping up in May, Ukrainian drone
strikes had managed to hit virtually all
of the land-based entrance points into
the Crimean Peninsula. From the bridges
over the North Crimean Canal in the
northwest that lead over the ismas of
Paracop to the Chongar bridge in the
center to the Henny Chensk bridge in the
east that leads into the Arabet spit and
all across the R280 highway of death
stretching all the way to Molita. The
result is that by midJune, the Ukrainian
414th Unmanned Strike Aviation Brigade
reported the Russia's military cargo
traffic along the R280 had crashed by an
astonishing 71% over a period of just 2
weeks. Satellite images have also
captured the scale of the damage on
these bridges that the Ukrainian drones
have inflicted, such as this image
captured over the Chongar Bridge in
central Crimea from midJu. This image
captured over the Henny Chesk bridge
leading into the Arabet spit from late
June. And this image captured over the
Stavke bridge that runs over the Crimean
Canal leading into the ismas of Paracop.
And these have been far from the only
logistical targets that the Ukrainians
have begun targeting around Crimea
recently. Around the Kirch Strait
between Russia's Cranar, Cryan occupied
Crimea. Ukrainian drone operations have
targeted oil depots on either side of
the strait in Kirch and Kavkaz that
Russia is historically relied upon to
supply Crimea and the whole southern
front with fuel. While on the 21st of
June, Ukrainian drones managed to hit
three out of the five Russian vehicle
fairies that travel across the street
that were set ablaze as well,
effectively shutting down Russia's ferry
service between the mainland and Crimea
in the process and severing yet another
one of Russia's vital supply arteries.
and satellite images once again managed
to capture the scale of Ukraine's recent
drone attacks here too. In this image
taken over the Crimean side of the Kur
Strait from the 22nd of June, you can
see thick billowing smoke from the
burning oil storage tanks in Kirch that
were struck by Ukrainian drones. While
you can see white smoke emanating out
from the Crimean bridge itself, which is
a new defense mechanism that the
Russians have developed to try and
obscure the bridge from drone attacks.
Smoke generating vehicles will drive out
onto the bridge during drone attacks and
start blowing smoke to try and hide the
bridge as seen more clearly by this
image where you can actually see the
smoke blowing vehicles on the bridge
doing their thing. Fuel storage depots
and power lines across Crimea itself
have also been repeatedly targeted. And
the end result of all of this is that
Crimea is not only increasingly running
out of fuel and supplies, but it's also
running out of possible supply routes to
get more fuel and supplies in,
especially with the tight restrictions
on trucks and fuel that are still in
place along the Crimean Bridge, too.
Crimea is indeed getting steadily
transformed by the Ukrainians into an
island surrounded by war and fire, and
it is already beginning to have
devastating consequences for the Russian
military and government. With fewer and
fewer supply routes in a Crimea being
reliably open and with more storage
sites getting struck, the availability
of fuel in the peninsula is becoming
increasingly scarce. Gasoline began
being rationed in Crimea by midmay that
led to miles long lineups at gas
stations, which led to Russian tourists
visiting Crimea from the mainland
bringing their own gas and jerry cans
with them. One of these tourists
reported to the Washington Post in
midJune that they witnessed cues at gas
stations in Crimea reaching more than 8
hours long. And then shortly afterwards
in late June, the Russian occupation
authorities in Crimea took the most
drastic step yet by temporarily banning
all fuel sales for civilians in the
peninsula entirely, reserving anything
left exclusively for the military and
essential services. The biggest sign yet
of just how dire the fuel crisis in
Crimea has got it. And the day after
that announcement was made, even further
restrictions on civilian life in Crimea
came into force. The Russian installed
governor of Sevastapole, the largest
city in Crimea home to more than 500,000
people, announced multiple new
supposedly temporary restrictions in
light of this difficult situation,
including the closure of all public
transportation after 10 p.m., the
closure of all large shops and cafes
after 8:00 p.m., and even the shutdown
of street lights in order to conserve
energy. Residents have even been urged
by the authorities to turn off their air
conditioners despite temperatures in
Sevastapole reaching nearly 30° C or 86
Fahrenheit. Energy blackouts across
Crimea become increasingly frequent that
are also disrupting water supplies that
rely on electrical pumps. While the
occupation government even just banned
the use of riding mopeds and motorbikes
at night due to their noise supposedly
hindering defenses against Ukrainian
drones. All sporting events, summer
camps, competitions, and training
sessions for children throughout Crimea
were also cancelled by the occupation
authorities, supposedly due to security
concerns, but really because of the lack
of fuel, at least through the 1st of
September as well. And worst of all for
the occupation authorities in Crimea,
all of this is taking place exactly when
Crimea usually experiences its peak
tourism season. Every summer since the
Russians conquered and annexed Crimea in
2014, millions of Russian tourists from
elsewhere in the country have visited
the peninsula every summer for its warm
weather, beautiful beaches, and famous
summer camps that date back to the
Soviet era. The escalation of the war in
2022 caused a slight decrease in the
number of summertime tourists visiting
since nobody could visit Crimea by air
any longer. But until recently, the war
was generally kept far enough away from
Crimea. Nearly 4 million summertime
tourists still visited Crimea just last
year in 2025, which was nearly as high
as the pre-war and precoid level tourist
visits were. And most of them all came
in their cars along the Crimean Bridge
across the Kirch Strait. With all of
this chaos going on in Crimea right now,
however, the summer 2026 tourism season
is quickly shaping up to be a
catastrophe. In June, Russian tourist
associations reported a 50% drop in
tourist bookings in Crimea compared with
the month before in May. While booking
in July and August are already down by
more than 30% compared to a year ago,
which will inevitably the
crucial summer holiday economic activity
in Crimea that the local occupation
government and residents always rely on.
On the 26th of June, when the occupation
authorities in Crimea formally declared
a state of emergency across the
peninsula, thousands of cars packed with
tourist and residents attempting to all
flee at once triggered a massive 15
kilometer long traffic jam on the
Crimean side of the Kurt Strait Bridge
leading back to the Russian mainland.
One of the most visible attempts at a
mass exodus out of Crimea yet seen
during the whole war. The consequences
of the logistical lockdown that's now
plaguing Crimea is also affecting the
Russian military's operations further to
the north along the front line as well.
The Crimean Peninsula with all of its
storage sites, depots, arsenals,
airfields, and military bases along with
its proximity to the Russian mainland
has been able to support the Russian
army's offensives in southern Ukraine
for years now. But with the peninsula
becoming increasingly locked down by
Ukraine's methodical drone campaign,
more and more of Russia's supply routes
will have to be shifted away to the more
vulnerable and exposed landbridge in the
north instead. This is critical because
stretching a truck supply route even by
an additional 80 to 100 km will reduce
the volume of supplies that a truck can
transport by 30% a day, which directly
results in the Russian military being
able to mount fewer and fewer assaults
along the front. The longer that Crimea
is locked down from a logistical
perspective, the weaker that Russia's
military operations in the occupied
regions of Hersan and Zaparisia will
become. Even Crimea's ability to serve
as an air base is also becoming
increasingly degraded as storage sites
and launchers on the peninsula are
increasingly becoming able to be
targeted by Ukraine's drones. It's even
been reported that Russia's mobile air
defense teams in Crimea tasked with
shooting down the drones are also having
to ration their fuel, which is reducing
their ability to stop the attacks from
getting even worse.
And all of this is increasingly becoming
a disaster of legitimacy for Vladimir
Putin. The way that Russia was able to
seize control over Crimea virtually
without any bloodshed in 2014 was widely
viewed as Putin's greatest geopolitical
triumph in Russia. It became the
keystone symbol of Russia's resurgence
to great power or even superpower status
in the 21st century. and it provided
Putin with a great deal of his mandate
to rule and popularity with the Russian
people. Now, however, with Russia's grip
on Crimea proving to be increasingly
tenuous, Ukraine is applying tremendous
amounts of pressure on Putin. If Ukraine
manages to make Russia's control over
Crimea unviable, and regular civilian
life on the peninsula difficult or even
impossible, then the Ukrainians will
gain major leverage in any future
negotiations on ending the war with the
Kremlin. Crimea is almost certainly not
returning back to Ukrainian control
again anytime soon, and the Ukrainian
military is still a long way from being
able to mount a successful attack to
retake it by force. But apparently,
instead, the Ukrainians can actually
keep making both life and military
operations in Crimea increasingly
unviable through this new mid-range
drone campaign that is systematically
destroying all of Russia's supply routes
into and out of the peninsula. And so
far, the Russians haven't been able to
figure out a successful enough counter
measure. If the situation continues,
pressure would build on Putin to
escalate or negotiate or risk a
humiliating mass population exodus from
Crimea like it seemed was taking place
near the end of June when the state of
emergency was declared and there was
that 15 km long traffic jam leading to
the only bridge out. And if there isn't
a ceasefire, then the pressure on Putin
will just keep on building and building
as this once great symbol of Russia's
restored imperial power continues
withering away under the mass of
Ukraine's relentless drone attacks. For
now, Crimea indeed appears to have been
transformed by the Ukrainians into an
island surrounded by war and fire.
Ultimately though, figuring out and
solving the geopolitical crisis in
Ukraine will likely be as difficult
going forward as it's already been for
more than a decade since Russian troops
first marched across the border and
seized Crimea in 2014. But something
that is very much figured out on the
other hand is what you should watch next
or at least put on your list and that's
the China that she grew up in. A grand
theory of Xihinping, which is a Nebula
exclusive, which means that it exists
only on the streaming service that
myself and a whole bunch of other
creators put together called Nebula.
Created by my friend Polyatter, this
documentary explores the dramatic rise
to power of Xihinping. From sleeping on
the floor of a cave to leading one of
the two global superpowers of the 21st
century, it's an incredible story that's
well worth your time and will help you
understand even more about the modern
world we live in. Then there were also
my own projects on Nebula like Mad
Kings, a show that explores the darker
histories of some of modern history's
most well-known dictators, including
other recent historical figures who have
clashed with the Western world like
Libya's Muamar Gaddafi and Iraq's U
Hussein, along with episodes covering
the reigns of North Korea's Kim Sunung
and Kim Jong-il that explore how they
were actually able to avoid a US
intervention. And then there's also my
other Nebula series called Modern
Conflicts, which explores modern wars,
battles, and conflicts in a level of
depth and detail that would never work
out on YouTube without triggering this
site's demonetization and age
restriction policies with episodes you
can watch covering the Israel
Palestinian conflict, Hamas's attack on
Israel on October 7th, the overthrow of
the Assad regime in Syria, and Israel's
invasion of the Gaza Strip that explain
the crucial backstory information you
need to understand what's currently
happening in the Middle East right now.
These are my own projects, but there's
also just so much good stuff on Nebula
from other creators right now that you
can watch, too. There's Day Pass, hosted
by Jason from Not Just Bikes, that
explores the world through the lens of
public transportation down on the
ground. If you ever wondered what ever
happened to Lindsay Ellis, she's been
making her usual documentaries on Nebula
for years now instead of YouTube.
There's Patrick Williams latest short
film, The Dinner Plan, featuring big
names like Griffin Newman and Zack
Cherry. There's abolish Everything, our
new comedy debate premise recorded live
in New York. Scav, a docky series
produced by the Wendover Productions and
Jetlag folks tracing the incredible
drama and unfoldings of the world's
largest annual scavenger hunt hosted at
the University of Chicago and oldest and
newest places by Joe Scott. A fulllength
documentary exploring the oldest and
newest rocks on the planet and what it
takes to actually visit them. I could
honestly keep going and going, but just
believe me when I say that with every
month that goes by, the Nebula catalog
keeps getting deeper, making becoming a
subscriber even better. But we also need
you to keep this whole cycle going. We
have a great deal running right now that
when you use my link at
nebula.tv/realifelorore TV/realife lore
or by scanning the QR code here on your
screen or by clicking the button. You'll
get a whole 50% off of an annual Nebula
subscription, which will bring the cost
for you down to just $30 for the entire
year or $250 a month, a small fraction
of the price of other streaming
services. As other streamers keep
raising their prices, this is an awesome
deal. And if you want to sign up for a
lifetime subscription to Nebula, never
deal with a monthly subscription ever
again, you can also get one for 40% off
right now for $300 as well. So give us a
shot and thank you so much for
supporting not only my own channel, but
all of the other creators who are
building Nebula with their own awesome
content as well. And as always, thank
you so much for watching.